Xian Xu

■ xian.xu@connect.ust.hk | 🏠 https://xxuxian.github.io/ | 🗣 CB3 0SZ, Cambridge, UK

Basic Information

Gender: Female Birthday: 1994-5 Writer, Interdisciplinary Computational Media and Arts Researcher Research interest: Data-driven Storytelling, Cinematic Arts, Arts Education in VR and the Metaverse, and Human-Computer Interaction. I am devoted to enhancing data-driven storytelling and arts education by extending not only the disciplinary depth but also the interdisciplinary breadth.

Education Background and Research Experience

Cambridge University, Research Visiting Fellow

Cambridge Digital Humanities, School of Arts and Humanities, work with Prof. Caroline Bassett

Oxford University, Research Visiting Fellow

Oxford e-Research Center, Department of Engineering Science, work with Prof. Min Chen

Peking University

Visualization Summer School, hosted by Prof. Xiaoru Yuan

The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

PhD in Computational Media and Arts, Supervised by Prof. Huamin Ou

The Central Academy of Drama

MFA in Drama and Film Studies, GPA (3.92/4.0) Ranking (1/25)

The Central Academy of Drama

BS in Directing (Film and TV Producing), GPA (3.88/4.0) Ranking (1/40)

Cambridge, UK

Apr. 2023 - Jul. 2023

Oxford, UK

Jan. 2023 - Mar. 2023

Beijing, China Jul. 2022

Hong Kong, China

Aug. 2020 - Aug. 2023

Beijing, China

Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2020

Beijing, China

Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2017

Publications _____

- [1] Xian Xu, Aoyu Wu, Leni Yang, Zheng Wei, Rong Huang, David Yip, Huamin Qu."Is It the End? Guidelines for Cinematic Endings in Data Videos" ACM CHI 2023. https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3544548.3580701
- [2] Xian Xu, Leni Yang, David Yip, Mingming Fan, Zheng Wei, Huamin Qu. "From 'Wow' to 'Why': Guidelines for Creating the Opening of a Data Video with Cinematic Styles" ACM CHI 2022. https://doi.org/10.1145/3491102.3501896
- [3] Xian Xu, Wai Tong, Zheng Wei, Meng Xia, Lik-Hang Lee, Huamin Qu. "Cinematography in the Metaverse: Exploring the Lighting Education on a Soundstage" IEEE VR Poster 2023. 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00128
- [4] Leni Yang, Xian Xu, Xingyu Lan, Ziyan Liu, Shunan Guo, Yang Shi, Huamin Qu, Nan Cao. "A Design Space for Applying the Freytag's Pyramid Structure to Data Stories" IEEE VIS 2021 (TVCG). 10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114774
- [5] Leni Yang, Aoyu Wu, Wai Tong, Xian Xu, Zheng Wei, Huamin Qu. "Understanding 3D data Videos: From Screens to Virtual Reality" IEEE Pacific Vis 2023 (Available at SSRN 4361223).
- [6] Xian Xu, Zelin Ye, Yuanzhe Jin, Leni Yang, Huamin Qu, Min Chen. "The Design Space of Short Technical Storytelling Videos: Through the Lens of Preview Videos in VIS Conferences" TVCG 2023 (Under Review).
- [7] Xian Xu, Wai Tong, Zheng Wei, Meng Xia, Lik-Hang Lee, Huamin Qu. "Cinematography in the Metaverse: Exploring the Lighting Education on a Soundstage" ISMAR 2023 (Under Review).
- [8] Zheng Wei*, Xian Xu*, Lik-Hang Lee, Wai Tong, Huamin Qu, Pan Hui. "Feeling Present! From Physical to Virtual Cinematography Lighting Education with Metashadow" ACM MM 2023 (Under Review).

Awards and Honors _____

Jan. 2023	Scholarship: "HKUST Overseas Research Award"	Hong Kong, China
Aug. 2020-2023	Scholarship: "Postgraduate Scholarship of HKUST"	Hong Kong, China
Jul. 2020	Honorary Title: "Excellent Postgraduate of Beijing"	Beijing, China
Dec.2019	Scholarship: "National Scholarship for PG Students"	Beijing, China
Dec.2017	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul. 2017	Honorary Title: "Excellent Undergraduate of Beijing"	Beijing, China
Dec.2016	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul.2016	Scholarship: "First-class Academic Award from CAD"	Beijing, China
Dec.2015	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul.2015	Scholarship: "First-class Academic Award from CAD"	Beijing, China
Dec.2014	Scholarship: "National Scholarship"	Beijing, China
Jul.2014	Scholarship: "First-class Academic Award from CAD"	Beijing, China

Teaching Experience _____

IDPO 2020 Cross-disciplinary Design Thinking, HKUST	Teaching Assistant
A	E-1- 2022 I 2022

Assist for Prof. Rong Zhang and Prof. Jinni Zhou

Feb. 2022 - Jun. 2022

CMAA 5008 Visual Communication, HKUST Teaching Assistant

Assist for Prof. David Yip Sep. 2021 - Jan. 2022

The Central Academy of Drama Counselor

Peking Opera, Dance Drama, Opera, and Film & TV Departments Sep. 2018 - Jul. 2020

Middle and Primary Schools in Beijing, China Drama Instructor

Drama and Film Arts Education Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2018

Work Experience and Creations _____

Data Visualization X Cinematic Arts	Writer and Designer
Four Cinematic Data Video Endings with Punctuation Marks	created in Sep. 2022
Arts Education & Technology Startup	Co-Founder

Art Mirror Network Technology Co. founded in Jan. 2019

Our Glamorous TimeScreenwriterTV Play of Zhejiang TV and Dragon TV in ChinaBroadcasted in Dec. 2018

I Like to be Independent

Writer

Bestseller in China Published in May 2017

Silent Love Screenwriter

Film of CCTV6 Created in 2016

Mind Reader Screenwriter and Director

Suspense-themed Microfilm

Screenwriter and Director

Created in 2015

Hurt Screenwriter and Director

Youth Campus-themed Microfilm

Created in 2014

AB Sides

Screenwriter and Director**

Youth Campus-themed Microfilm Created in 2014

Personal Skills _____

Languages English (Fluent), Cantonese (Native), Mandarin (Native)

Personality Optimistic, curious about new things, hardworking, and easygoing

Specialty Project management and teamwork